78 The next day he did not leave the house, and, indeed, spent most of the time
in his own room, sick with a wild terror of dying, and yet indifferent to life
itself. The consciousness of being hunted, snared, tracked down, had begun to dominate
him. If the tapestry did but tremble in the wind, he shook. The dead leaves that
were blown against the Leed pains seemed to him like his own wasted resolutions and wild
regrets. When he closed his eyes, he saw again the sailor’s face peering through
the Mist stained glass, and horror seemed once more to lay its hand upon his
heart. But perhaps it had been only his fancy that had called vengeance out of
the night and set the hideous shapes of punishment before
him. Actual life was chaos but but there was something terribly logical in the
imagination. It was the imagination that set remorse to dog the feet of
sin. It was the imagination that made each crime bear its misshapen brood. In
the common world of fact the wicked were not punished, nor the good rewarded.
Success was given to the strong, failure thrust upon the weak. That was
all. Besides, had any stranger been prowling around the house, he would have
been seen by the servants or the keepers. Had any foot marks been found on
the flower beds the gardeners would have reported it. Yes, it had been merely fancy
cibil Vain's brother had not come back to kill him. He had sailed away in his
ship to founder in some winter sea. From him, at any rate, he was safe. Why, the man
did not know who he was, could not know who he was. The mask of youth had saved
him. And yet if it had been merely an illusion, how terrible it was to think that conscience
could raise such fearful phantoms, and give them visible form, and make them
move before one! What sort of life would his be if, day and night, shadows of his
crime were to peer at him from silent corners, to mock him from secret places,
to whisper in his ear as he sat at the
feast, to wake him with icy fingers as he lay asleep!
As the thought crept through his brain, he grew pale with terror, and the air
seemed to him to have become suddenly colder. Oh! in what a wild hour of madness
he had killed his friend! How ghastly the mere memory of the scene! He saw it all
again. Each hideous detail came back to him with added horror. Out of the black
cave of time, terrible and SED in scarlet, rose the image of his
sin. When Lord Henry came in at 6:00 he found him crying as one whose heart will
break. It was not till the third day that he ventured to go
out. There was something in the clear pine scented air of that winter morning
that seemed to bring him back his joyousness and his ardor for
life. But it was not merely the physical conditions of environment that had
caused the change. His own nature had revolted against the excess of anguish
that had sought to maim and mar the perfection of its calm. With subtle and
finely wrought temperaments it is always so. Their strong passions must either
bruise or bend. They either slay the man, or themselves die. Shallow sorrows and
shallow loves live on. The loves and sorrows that are great are destroyed by
their own plenitude. Besides, he had convinced himself that he had been the
victim of a terror stricken imagination, and look back now on his
fears with something of pity and not a little of contempt.
After breakfast, he walked with the duchess for an hour in the garden and
then drove across the park to join the shooting party The crisp frost lay like
salt upon the grass. The sky was an inverted cup of blue metal. A thin film
of ice bordered the flat Reed grown lake.
At the corner of the Pinewood he caught sight of Sir Jeffrey K Clon the
duchess’s brother, jerking two spent cartridges out of his gun. He jumped from
the cart, and having told the groom to take the mayare home, made his way
towards his guest through the withered bracken and rough undergrowth. “Have you had good sport
Jeffrey he asked. “Not very good, Dorian. I think most of the birds have gone to the
open. I dare say it will be better after lunch, when we get to new
ground.” Dorian strolled along by his side.
The keen aromatic air, the brown and red lights that glimmered in the wood, the
horar cries of the beaters ringing out from time to time, and the sharp snaps of
the guns that followed, fascinated him and filled him with a sense of
delightful freedom. He was dominated by the carelessness of happiness, by the
high indifference of joy. Suddenly from a lumpy Tusk of old grass some 20 yards in
front of them, with black tipped ears erect and long hinder limbs throwing it
forward, started a hair It bolted for a thicket of alers Sir Jeffrey put his gun to his
shoulder, but there was something in the animals grace of movement that strangely
charmed Dorian Gray, and he cried out at once, “Don’t shoot it Jeffrey Let it live.”
“What nonsense, Dorian!” laughed his companion, and as the hair bounded into the thicket, he
fired. There were two cries heard, the cry of a hair in pain, which is dreadful, the
cry of a man in agony, which is worse. “Good heavens! I have hit a beater!”
exclaimed Sir Jeffrey What an ass the man was to get in front of the guns! Stop
shooting there!” he called out at the top of his voice. “A man is hurt.” The
headkeeper came running up with a stick in his hand. “Where, sir? Where is he?” he
shouted. At the same time, the firing ceased along the line. “Here,” answered Sir
Jeffrey angrily, hurrying towards the thicket. “Why on earth don’t you keep your
men back? Spoiled my shooting for the day.” Dorian watched them as they plunged
into the older Clump brushing the lithe swinging branches aside. In a few moments
they emerged, dragging a body after them into the sunlight. He turned away in horror. It
seemed to him that misfortune followed wherever he went. He heard Sir Jeffrey
ask if the man was really dead, and the affirmative answer of the keeper. The
wood seemed to him to have become suddenly alive with faces. There was the trampling of myriad
feet and the low buzz of voices. A great copper breasted pheasant came beating
through the boughs overhead. After a few moments— —that were
to him, in his perturbed state, like endless hours of
pain— —he felt a hand laid on his shoulder.
He started and looked round. “Dorian,” said Lord Henry, “I better tell them that the
shooting is stopped for today It would not look well to go
on.” “I wish it was stopped forever Harry,” he answered said bitterly. “The whole
thing is hideous and cruel. Is the man He could not finish the
sentence. “I am afraid so,” rejoined Lord Henry. “He got the whole charge of shot in
his chest. He must have died almost instantaneously. Come; let us go home.” They
walked side by side in the direction of the avenue for nearly 50 yards without
speaking. Then Dorian looked at Lord Henry and said, with a heavy sigh, “It is a
bad omen, Harry, a very bad omen.” “What is?” asked Lord Henry. “Oh! this
accident, I suppose. My dear fellow, it can’t be helped. It was the man’s own
fault. Why did he get in front of the guns? Besides, it is nothing to us. It is
rather awkward for Jeffrey of course. It does not do to Peppa beaters. It makes
people think that one is a wild shot. And Jeffrey is not; he shoots very straight.
But there's no use talking about the matter.” Dorian shook his head. “It is a bad
omen, Harry. I feel as if something horrible were going to happen to some of
us. To myself, perhaps,” he added, passing his hand over his eyes, with a gesture of
pain. The elder man laughed. “The only horrible thing in the world is on WE
Dorian. That is the one sin for which there is no forgiveness. But we are not likely to
suffer from it unless these fellows keep chattering about this thing at
dinner. I must tell them that the subject is to be
tabooed. As for omens, there is no such thing as an omen. Destiny does not send
us heralds. She is too wise or too cruel for that. Besides, what on earth could
happen to you, Dorian? You have everything in the world
that a man can want. There is no one who would not be delighted to change places with
you.” “There is no one with with whom I would not change places, Harry. Don’t
laugh like that I'm telling you the truth. The wretched peasant who has just
died is better off than I am. I have no terror of death. It is the coming of
death that terrifies me it's monstrous wings seem to wheel in the leaden air
around me. Good heavens! don’t you see a man moving behind the trees there,
watching me, waiting for me?” Lord Henry looked in the direction in which the
trembling glove hand was pointing. “Yes,” he said, smiling, “I see the gardener waiting
for you. I suppose he wants to ask you what flowers you wish to have on the
table tonight How absurdly nervous you are, my dear fellow! You must come and see
my doctor, when we get back to town.” Dorian heaved a sigh of relief as
he saw the gardener approaching. The man touched his hat,
glanced for a moment at Lord Henry in a hesitating manner, and then produced a
letter, which he handed to his master. “Her Grace told me to wait for an
answer,” he murmured. Dorian put the letter into his pocket. “Tell her Grace that I'm
coming in,” he said, coldly. The man turned round and went rapidly in the direction of the
house. “How fond women are of doing dangerous things!” laughed Lord Henry. “It
is one of the qualities in them that I admire most. A woman will flirt with
anybody in the world as long as other people are looking on.”
“How fond you are of saying dangerous things, Harry! In the present instance, you
are quite astray. I like the duess very much, but I don’t love her.” “And the
duchess loves you very much, but she likes you less, so you are excellently
matched.” “You are talking scandal, Harry, and there is never any basis for
scandal.” “The basis of every scandal is an immoral certainty,” said Lord Henry, lighting a
cigarette. “You sacrifice anybody, Harry, for the sake of an
epigram.” “The world goes to the altar of its own accord,” was the
answer. “I wish I could love,” cried Dorian Gray with a deep note of pathos in his
voice. “But I seem to have lost the passion and forgotten the desire I'm too
much concentrated on myself. My own personality has become a burden to me. I
want to escape, to go away, to forget. It
was silly of me to come down here at all.
I think I shall send a wire to Harvey to
have the yacht got ready. On a yacht one is safe.” “Safe from what, Dorian? You are in
some trouble. Why not tell me what it is?
You know I would help you.” “I can’t tell you, Harry,” he answered sadly. “And I dare
say it is only a fancy of mine. This unfortunate accident has upset me. I have
a horrible presentiment that something of the kind may happen to me.” “What nonsense!”
“I hope it is, but I can’t help feeling it.
Ah! here is the duchess, looking like Artemis in a tailor made gown. You see we
have come back, Duchess.” “I have heard all about it, Mr.
Gray,” she answered. “Poor Jeffrey is terribly upset. And it seems that you asked him
not to shoot the hair How curious!” “Yes, it was very curious. I don’t
know what made me say it. Some whim, I suppose.
It looked the loveliest of little live things. But I am sorry they told you
about the man. It is a hideous subject.” “It is an annoying subject,” broke
in Lord Henry. “It has no psychological value at all. Now if Jeffrey had done the
thing on purpose, how interesting he would be! I should like to know someone
who had committed a real murder.” “How horrid of you, Harry!” cried the
duchess. “Isn’t it, Mr. Gray? Harry, Mr. Gray is ill again he's going to
faint.” Dorian drew himself up with an effort and smiled. “It is nothing dues he murmured; “my
nerves are dreadfully out of order. That is all I'm afraid I walked too far this
morning. I didn’t hear what Harry said.
Was it very bad? You must tell me some other time. I
think I must go and lie down. You will excuse me, won’t
you?” They had reached the great flight of steps that led from the conservatory
onto the terrace. As the glass door closed behind Dorian, Lord Henry turned
and looked at the duchess with his slumberous eyes. “Are you very much in love with him?”
he asked. She did not answer for some time, but stood gazing at the
landscape. “I wish I knew,” she said at last. He shook his head. “Knowledge would
be fatal. It is the uncertainty that charms one mist makes things
wonderful.” “One may lose one’s way.” “All ways end at the same point, my
dear Gladis What is that?” “Disillusion.” “It was my debut in life,” she sighed. “It came to you
crowned.” “I am tired of strawberry leaves.” “They become you.” “Only in
public.” “You would miss them,” said Lord Henry. “I will not part with a petal.”
“Monmouth has ears.” “Old age is dull of hearing.” “Has he never been jealous?” “I wish
he had been.” He glanced about as if in search of something. “What are you looking
for?” she inquired. “The button from your foil,” he answered. “You have dropped it.” She
laughed. “I have still the mask.” “It makes your eyes lovelier,” was his
reply. She laughed again. Her teeth showed like white seeds in a scarlet
fruit. Upstairs, in his own room, Dorian Gray was lying on a sofa, with terror in
every tingling fiber of his body. Life had suddenly become too hideous a burden for him to
bear. The dreadful death of the unlucky beater, shot in the thicket like a wild
animal, had seemed to him to prefigure death for himself also. He had nearly
swooned at what Lord Henry had said in a chance mood of cynical
jesting. At 5:00 he rang his bell for his servant and gave him orders to pack his
things for the night express to town, and to have the Bram at the door by
8:30 He was determined not to sleep another night at Selby Royal. It was an
ill omened place. Death walked there in the sunlight. The grass of the forest had
been spotted with blood. Then he wrote a note to Lord Henry, telling him that he
was going up to town to consult his doctor and asking him to entertain his
guests in his absence. As he was putting it into to the envelope, a knock came to
the door, and his valet informed him that the headkeeper wished to see him. He
frowned and bit his lip. “Send him in,” he muttered, after some
moments’ hesitation. As soon as the man entered, Dorian pulled his checkbook out
of a drawer and spread it out before him. “I suppose you have come about the
unfortunate accident of this morning, Thornton?” he said, taking up a pen. “Yes, sir,”
answered the gamekeeper.
“Was the poor fellow married? Had he any people dependent on him?” asked Dorian,
looking bored. “If so, I should not like them to be left in want, and will send
them any sum of money you may think necessary.” “We don’t know who he is, sir.
That is what I took the liberty of coming to you about.” “Don’t know who he is?”
said Dorian, listlessly. “What do you mean?
Wasn’t he one of your men?” “No, sir. Never saw him before. Seems like a sailor, sir.”
The pen dropped from Dorian Gray’s hand, and he felt as if his heart had suddenly
stopped beating. “A sailor?” he cried out.
“Did you say a sailor?” “Yes, sir. He looks as
if he had been a sort of sailor; tattooed on both arms, and that kind of thing.” “Was
there anything found on him?” said Dorian, leaning forward and looking at the man
with startled eyes. “Anything that would tell his name?” “Some money, sir— —not much, and a six
shooter There was no name of any kind. A decent looking man, sir, but rough likee A sort
of sailor we think.” Dorian started to his feet. A terrible hope fluttered past him.
He clutched at it madly. “Where is the body?” he
exclaimed. “Quick! I must see it at once.” “It is in an empty stable in the Home Farm,
sir. The folk don’t like to have that sort of thing in their houses. They say a
corpse brings bad luck.” “The Home Farm! Go there at once and meet me. Tell one of
the grooms to bring my horse round. No.
Never mind. I’ll go to the stables myself.
It will save time.” In less than a quarter of an hour,
Dorian Gray was galloping down the long avenue as hard as he could
go. The trees seemed to sweep past him in spectral procession, and wild shadows to
fling themselves across his path. Once the May swerved at a white gate poost
and nearly threw him. He lashed her across the neck with his crop. She
clefted the dusky air like an arrow. The stones flew from her
Hooves At last he reached the Home Farm.
Two men were loitering in the yard. He leapt from the saddle and threw the
rains to one of them. In the farthest stable a light was glimmering. Something
seemed to tell him that the body was there, and he hurried to the door and put
his hand upon the latch. There he paused for a moment, feeling that he was on the
brink of a discovery that would either make or mar his life. Then he thrust the
door open and entered. On a heap of sacking in the far
corner was lying the dead body of a man dressed in a coarse shirt and a pair of
blue trousers. A spotted handkerchief had been placed over the face. A coarse
candle, stuck in a bottle, sputtered beside it. Dorian Gray shuddered. He felt
that his could not be the hand to take the handkerchief away, and called out to
one of the farm servants to come to him.
“Take that thing off the face. I wish to see it,” he said, clutching at the doorpost for
support. When the farm servant had done so, he stepped forward. A cry of joy broke
from his lips. The man who had been shot in the thicket was James vain He stood
there for some minutes looking at the dead body. As he rode home, his eyes were
full of tears, for he knew he was safe